A Guide to the Sold Property Files of the Virginia Dept. of General Services, 1928-2021.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Sold Property Files of the Virginia Dept. of General Services,
1928-2021.
The Library of Virginia
43931, 51674, 53922
Virginia. Dept. of General Services.
25 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Arranged in original order.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions
Acquisition Information
Accession 43931 was transferred by the Dept. of General Services on 08/14/2008.
Accession 51674 was transferred by the Dept. of General Services on 11/05/2015.
Accession 53922 was transferred by the Dept. of General Services on 06/20/2023.
Historical Information
The mission of the Dept. of General Services is to provide supportive services to other state agencies, local political subdivisions as appropriate, in the areas of laboratory services; maintenance, operation and construction of facilities; land management; land and facilities acquisition; disposal and sale of material and supplies; risk management; and other related activities. The Commission on State Governmental Management recommended the creation of the Dept. of General Services to be comprised of the then existing Dept. of Purchases and Supplies, Division of Engineering and Buildings, Division of Consolidated Laboratory Services, Dept. of Property Records and Insurance, and several other state agencies functions which were subsequently determined by appropriate authorities to be left outside of the organization of this department.
In 1976, the General Assembly passed H.B. 1240 which called for the establishment of the position of a director of the department and required the appointee to prepare a plan for the organization of this department with implementing legislation. This was accomplished and the 1977 session of the General Assembly enacted Chapter 672 which created the Dept. of General Services. Consistent with this statute, the department was officially implemented on July 1, 1978. This brought together, under the umbrella of the major department, the Dept. of Purchases and Supply, the Division of Engineering, the Division of Consolidated Laboratory Services, and the Dept. of Property Records and Insurance, now called Office of Risk Management. Also included under the umbrella of the authority of the Dept. of General Services are several boards, appeal boards and review councils which are: Consolidated Laboratory Services Advisory Board; Purchase and Supply Appeal Board; Art and Architectural Review and Council and the State Insurance Advisory Board.
Major activities of the department are to maintain and operate facilities at the seat of government; assist in the administration of the capital outlay budget of the Commonwealth; to assist in acquisition of real property either by lease or purchase; to perform centralized purchasing functions of the Commonwealth; to dispose of surplus real property and material and supplies; to provide a comprehensive risk management insurance program for all agencies and institutions; to operate a centralized purchasing and warehousing function for supplying State agencies and certain political subdivisions with equipment and supplies; to acquire or provide printing services for State agencies and institutions; provide central mail and messenger service for State agencies in the area of the seat of government; provide laboratory research and scientific services in the area of environmental sciences; forensic science, microbiology, and product regulation; to provide training to law enforcement personnel in the collection and preservation of evidence; and to conduct programs on inspection and certification of certain laboratories through the state.
Scope and Content
This series consists of documentation on state owned properties that have been sold. May include correspondence, deeds, environmental assessments, appraisal reports, leases, clippings and various other reports and related materials. Includes properties owned by the Dept. of Agriculture and Consumer Services (VDACS), Alcoholic Beverage Control (ABC), Center for Innovative Technology (CIT), Dept. of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services (DBHDS), Dept. of Conservation and Recreation (DCR), Dept. of Corrections (DOC), Dept. of Forestry (DOF), Dept. of Game and Inland Fisheries (DGIF), Dept. of General Services (DGS), Dept. of Juvenile Justice (DJJ), Dept. of Military Affairs (DMA), Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy (DMME), Dept. of Transportation (VDOT), University of Mary Washington (UMW), University of Virginia (UVA), Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU), Virginia Employment Commission (VEC), Virginia Museum of Fine Art (VMFA), and the Virginia State Police (VSP), among others.
Contents List
- Sold Property Files of the Virginia Dept. of General Services, 1933-2021.
  - Accession 43931 (1989-2003)., Extent: 6 cu. ft.
    - DOC - Halfway House (Norfolk), 1989. (Box 1)
    - ABC - Pound, Va., 1989. (Box 1)
    - VSP - Area 18 Headquarters, 1997. (Box 1)
    - ABC - Store 223, 1999. (Box 1)
    - DOC - Pine Crest Learning Center, 1999. (Box 1)
    - DMME - Big Stone Gap, 1999. (Box 1)
    - DCR - Fort Boykin, 1999. (Box 1)
    - DMV - Newport News Branch Office, 1999. (Box 2)
    - DMV - Annandale, 1999. (Box 2)
    - DOC - Pine Crest Learning Center, 2000. (Box 2)
    - DOC - Manassas, 2000. (Box 2)
    - DGS - Central Warehouse (12th and Dinwiddie St.), 2001. (Box 2)
    - UVA - Blue Ridge Hospital, 2001. (Box 2)
    - VDOT - Pine Chapel (Hampton), 2001. (Box 2)
    - UVA - 1/6 interest in property in Louisiana, 2002. (Box 3)
    - VPI - Winchester Fruit Research Station, 2002. (Box 3)
    - DGIF - Administration Office (Roanoke), 2002. (Box 3)
    - DMA - Danville Maintenance Shop, 2002. (Box 3)
    - VDOT - Winchester, 2003. (Box 3)
    - DOC - Fairfax 501A-4701, 2003. (Box 3)
    - DMA - Richland Armory, 2003. (Box 3)
    - Main Street, 1987-1998. (Box 4)
    - Main Street, 1998-2000. (Box 5)
    - DGS - Parking deck, 2003. (Box 6)
    - DCR - Kiptopeke Park, 2003. (Box 6)
    - Mason Neck State Park, 2003. (Box 6)
    - New River Trail State Park (Exchange Town of Fries), 2003. (Box 6)
    - New Trail State Park (Whitt acquisition), 2003. (Box 6)
    - Fife Pinnacle (Natural Area Preserve), 2003. (Box 6)
    - Buffalo Mountain (Natural Area Preserve), 2003. (Box 6)
    - UVA - 1/6 interest in property (Louisiana), 2003. (Box 6)
    - Boothes Woods acquisition, 2003. (Box 6)
    - Cleaveland Bearing (Natural Area Preserve), 2003. (Box 6)
    - Difficult Creek (Natural Area Preserve), 2003. (Box 6)
    - Fairfew Glades (Natural Area Preserve), 2003. (Box 6)
    - Mt. Join Pond (Natural Area Preserve), 2003. (Box 6)
    - 7 Bins (Natural Area Preserve) - Camp Lumpton, 2003. (Box 6)
    - Clover Hollow (Natural Area Preserve) - Acquisition, 2003. (Box 6)
    - Cherry Orchard Bog (Natural Area Preserve) - Blue Sky Timber LLC acquisition, 2003. (Box 6)
    - Mutton Hunk Fen (Natural Area Preserve), 2003. (Box 6)
    - Longwood University (506 Griffin Blvd., 610 Griffin Blvd., 607 Race St.), 2003. (Box 6)
    - James Madison University (567-601 University Blvd.), 2003. (Box 6)
    - Virginia Commonwealth University (301 Cary St.), 2003. (Box 6)
    - Christopher Newport University (67 N. Moores Ln.), 2003. (Box 6)
  - Accession 51674 (1928-2010)., Extent: 8 cu. ft.
    - UVA - Seward Forest, 1928-1975. (Box 1)
    - VCU - President's residence, 1969-1978. (Box 1)
    - UVA - Blue Ridge Hospital, 1978-2001. (Box 1)
    - DOC - Floyd Correctional Field Unit #5, 1946-1986. (Box 1)
    - DCHD - Richlands Tazewell Co., 1989-1994. (Box 1)
    - DMA - 5 acres at Camp Pendleton, 1994-1997. (Box 1)
    - DOC - Manassas Parcel 3.74 acres, Prince William Co., 2000. (Box 1)
    - UMW - Rowe Tract 3, Fredericksburg, 1977-2002. (Box 1)
    - DOC - Staff House - 1415 Ashton, Lunenburg Co., 1994-2004. (Box 1)
    - DOC - Greensville CC Staff House - 305 Pine Street, 1992-2004. (Box 1)
    - DGS - Main Street Station, Sale to City of Richmond, 1965-2009. (Box 1)
    - VSP - Area 43 Office, Danville, 1961-2005. (Box 1)
    - Haynesville CC Staff Housing - 1333 Hoskins Rd., Tappahannock, 1993-2005. (Box 1)
    - DOC - Lunenburg CC Staff House - 1511 Sixth St., Victoria, 1995-2005. (Box 2)
    - DOC - Red Onion Prison Staff Housing - 180 Phipps Cir., Clintwood, 1984-2005. (Box 2)
    - DOC - Staff House - 82 LeSueur St., Dillwyn, 1998-2005. (Box 2)
    - DOC - Greensville CC Staff Housing - 213 Holly Ave., 1998-2005. (Box 2)
    - DOC - Staff Housing - 1323 Hoskins Dr., Tappahannock, 1988-2005. (Box 2)
    - DOC - Staff House - 938 Phillis Rd., Boykin, 2003-2005. (Box 2)
    - VDOT - Chain Bridge Road Highway 123, Fairfax Co., 1939-2005. (Box 3)
    - DOC - Staunton Correctional Center, 1925-2005. (Box 4)
    - DJJ - Camp Washington, Isle of Wight Co., 1982-2011. (Box 4)
    - DOC - Brunswick CC Staff Housing - 1006 Brooks, Lawrenceville, 1987-2005. (Box 4)
    - DOC - VCCW Staff Housing - 4192 Campbell Rd., Troy, 1994-2005. (Box 5)
    - DOC - Tidewater Correctional Unit, Chesapeake, 1982-2005. (Box 5)
    - DOC - Staff House - 601 Willow Oak, Greensville Co., 2005. (Box 5)
    - DOC - Indian Creek CC Asst. Warden Residence - 736 Willow Oak, Chespeake, 1993-2006. (Box 5)
    - DOC - Dillwyn CC Staff Housing - 24 Simms Rd., 1989-2006. (Box 5)
    - VDOT - Starkey Area Headquarters, Roanoke Co., 1988-2006. (Box 6)
    - VDOT - New Kent Area Headquarters, New Kent Co., 1959-2007. (Box 6)
    - VDOT - Old Bartlett Area Headquarters, Isle of Wight Co., 1949-2006. (Box 6)
    - DGIF - Staunton Field Office, Augusta Co., 1968-2006. (Box 6)
    - DCR - George Washington Grist Mill Historic Site, 1932-2008. (Box 6)
    - VEC - Charlottesville Office, 1985-2008. (Box 7)
    - VDOT - Whaleyville Area Headquarters, Suffolk, 1961-2009. (Box 7)
    - VDOT - West Point Area Headquarters, West Point, 1992-2009. (Box 7)
    - DMA - Winchester Armory, 1976-2009. (Box 7)
    - DMA - Powhatan Armory, 1981-2009. (Box 7)
    - VCCS - Tidewater Community College TCCREF, Suffolk, 1959-2010. (Box 7)
    - DGS - Roanoke parking lot, 1985-2010. (Box 7)
    - VEC - Petersburg Local Office, 1988-2010. (Box 7)
    - DMA - Altavista Armory, Campbell Co., 1962-2010. (Box 8)
    - VDACS - Lab building, Harrisonburg, 1940-2010. (Box 8)
    - DOF - Staunton Regional Office, 1958-2010. (Box 8)
    - DGS - Abingdon Lab, Washington Co., 1961-2010. (Box 8)
  - Accession 53922 (1933-2021)., Extent: 11 cu. ft.
    - VSP - State Police Headquarters Area 4 - Deed, 1961-2004. (Box 1)
    - VDOT New Kent AHQ, 1959-2014. (Box 1)
    - VSP - Headquarters Area 29 - Buchanon Co., 1965-2008. (Box 1)
    - Brunswick CC Coal Unload, 1983-2010. (Box 1)
    - VDOT Residency and AHQ-Surplus, 1974-2011. (Box 1)
    - VDOT Amherst Residency, 1940-2011. (Box 1)
    - Carter's Mountain tower, 1933-2011. (Box 1)
    - DOC - 7 North 2nd Street, Richmond, 1955-2011. (Box 1)
    - VDOT Old Church AHQ, Hanover Co., 1955-2011. (Box 1)
    - VDOT Potts Creek Storage lot, Alleghany Co., 1989-2012. (Box 1)
    - VDACS - Accomack Inspection Office, 2011-2012. (Box 1)
    - VDOT Abingdon Storage Area, Washington Co., 2010-2012. (Box 1)
    - DGS - Former Tax Building, Richmond, 1947-2011. (Box 1)
    - VDOT Pouncey Tract / Short Pump AHQ, Henrico Co., 1969-2012. (Box 1)
    - VDOT Markham Storage Lot, Fauquier Co., 1966-2012. (Box 1)
    - VDOT Dewitt Storage Lot, Dinwiddie Co., 1955-2012. (Box 1)
    - DCR - Smiley property, 1999-2012. (Box 1)
    - DOF Brunswick Office, 2012. (Box 1)
    - Burgess Area Headquarters, 1974-2012. (Box 1)
    - DOF Farmville Regional Office, 1948-2012. (Box 1)
    - DBHDS - Duffield GH, Scott Co., 1987-2013. (Box 1)
    - DBHDS - Southwestern Mental Health Institute - Rogers Group Home, 1986-2013. (Box 1)
    - Route 624 Storage Area, 1966-2013. (Box 1)
    - DBHDS - Cumberlant Mountain Group Home, 1985-2013. (Box 1)
    - DBHDS - New River Group Home, Pulaski Co., 1985-2013. (Box 1)
    - Farmville Area HQ, 1937-2013. (Box 1)
    - Dept. of Forestry, Prince George County Office, 1990-2013. (Box 1)
    - Carroll / Grayson Co. Office, 1967-2013. (Box 1)
    - DBHDS CSH 09, Diwiddie, 2010-2013. (Box 2)
    - DGS Williamsburg Ave, Richmond, 1959-2013. (Box 2)
    - University of Mary Washington - MMM Germanna Archaeological Site, Orange Co., 1990-2013. (Box 2)
    - Starkey Road Area Headquargers, 2006-2013. (Box 2)
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts - The Oaks 307 Stockton Lane, 1976-2013. (Box 2)
    - DOC Tazewell Correctional Unit #31, 1958-2013. (Box 2)
    - Dept. of Forestry Sandston District Office, 1950-2014. (Box 2)
    - Goochland Co. Office, 1989-2014. (Box 2)
    - VDACS, 1952-2014. (Box 2)
    - Washington Area Headquarters, 1953-2014. (Box 2)
    - South Brunswick Area Headquarters, 1957-2014. (Box 2)
    - Powers Taylor Building, 1981-1988. (Box 2)
    - DGS Office Building - Surplus, 2011-2014. (Box 2)
    - Albemarle Greene Storage Area, 1973-2014. (Box 2)
    - VDOT Storage Lot - Surplus, 1974-2014. (Box 2)
    - Route 711 Storage Area, 1962-2014. (Box 2)
    - Orange Area Headquarters, 1950-2014. (Box 2)
    - Holocaust Museum, 1989-2005. (Box 3)
    - DGS - Extra attic, 1989-1995. (Box 3)
    - VDACS - Southwest Virginia Farmer's Market (Carroll Co.), 1989-2015. (Box 4)
    - DGIF - Staunton Field, 1968-2006. (Box 4)
    - DOF - Spotsylvania Co. Office, 1964-2015. (Box 4)
    - VDACS - Warrenton Diagnostic Lab, 1950-2018. (Box 4)
    - Batesville Warehouse, 1951-2016. (Box 4)
    - Southside Virginia Training Center, 1960-2016. (Box 4)
    - DMA - Radford Armory, 1954-2014. (Box 4)
    - DMA - Big Stone Gap Armory, 1968-2015. (Box 4)
    - Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind - Hampton, 1949-2019. (Box 4)
    - VEC - Harrisonburg Local Office, 2016. (Box 5)
    - DMA - Chatham Armory, 1954-2016. (Box 5)
    - DGIF Headquarters, 1965-2016. (Box 5)
    - Deed conveying certain subaqueous lands in the James River, 1993-1999. (Box 5)
    - SSP 520-014-1, CFU 29, 1982-1985. (Box 5)
    - ABC - Income lease (Glant), 2006-2015. (Box 6)
    - ABC - Alexandria, 2007-2011. (Box 6)
    - Income - Parking Lot License, 2008-2011. (Box 6)
    - ABC - Alexandria (Clarett), 1969-2011. (Box 6)
    - ABC - Alexandria (901 N. Asaph St.), 2005-2008. (Box 6)
    - Hawks Nest Golf Development Co., 2003-2006. (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 2005-2015. (Box 7)
    - Cheatham Annex - Agreement with York Co., 1991-2021. (Box 8)
    - Cheatham Annex, 1985-2015. (Box 9)
    - Cheatham Annex sale, 2007-2021. (Box 9)
    - Cheatham Annex - Deed / Dept. of Emergency Services, 1981-2004. (Box 9)
    - Hawks Nest Golf Course, 2001-2004. (Box 9)
    - DMA - Franklin Armory, 1952-2020. (Box 9)
    - Center for Innovative Technology, 2012-2018. (Box 10)
    - Center for Innovative Technology - Expired lease and correspondence, 1989-2018. (Box 10)
    - Center for Innovative Technology - Holly, 2015. (Box 10)
    - Center for Innovative Technology - Miscellaneous, 1989-2020. (Box 10)
    - VDOT - Brown Store Area Headquarters, 1954-2021. (Box 11)
    - DGIF - Northlake Headquarters, 2012-2021. (Box 11)
    - VEC - Norfolk Office, 1975-2020. (Box 11)